SAMUEL CARLEIAL FERNANDES

DOCTOR OF NATURAL SCIENCES



Birth: 26/07/1984, Fortaleza, Brazil

Nationality: Brazilian

Visa: residence permit (Germany)
Status: lives with partner and child
Webpage: https://samuel-carleial.github.io/
E-mail: samuel.carleial@uni-konstanz.de

Objective

I have always been very keen to learn about the world and acquire knowledge. Due to my Brazilian roots, I decided to become a biologist, so that I could understand the natural world and make important discoveries. After several years of experience, however, I noticed that the human component has unquestionably a crucial part in my plan of being a scientist. Today, I want to engage in work that I am passionate about, but also that is meaningful and has an impact in society.

Current position

08/2017 - now Post-Doctoral Researcher (100%), Clinical and Neuropsychology, Elbert Lab, University of Konstanz, Germany

<u>projects</u>: Narrative exposure therapy for traumatised offenders in North Kivu, Effect of narrative exposure therapy versus treatment as usual: a randomized controlled trial in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, amongst others <u>activities</u>: data management and analysis, statistical modelling, student supervision, scientific research,

project management, funding acquisition, international collaboration

Education

04/2013 - 07/2017 PhD in Biological Sciences (Dr. rer. nat.), University of Konstanz, Germany

in association with the Max Planck Research School for Organismal Biology (IMPRS), Germany

supervisors: Dr. Marc Stift and Dr. Mark van Kleunen

dissertation: The early steps of plant mating system evolution

grade: cum laude

01/2009 - 07/2011 MSc. in Biological Sciences (Systematics), National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico

supervisor: Dr. Alfonso Delgado-Salinas

thesis: Floral biology of Aeschynomene amorphoides

grade: honorific mention

01/2002 - 02/2007 BSc. & Lic. in Biological Sciences, Federal University of Ceará, Brazil

supervisor: Dr. Christian Westerkamp

thesis: Why are the nectaries in oiticica plants so large and oblique?

grade: 8759 I.R.A. (Brazilian grade)

Awards & Grants

04/2021	Research Seed Capital (RISC), MKW Baden-Wurttemberg and University of Konstanz; 99,990.40 €
03/2019	Young Scholar Fund (YSF), University of Konstanz; amount: 6,330 €
06/2018	Independent Research Grant (Zukunftskolleg), University of Konstanz; 4,740 €
2013 - 2017	Stipend for doctoral studies (CNPq and Max Planck Institute); 1,365 € per month (4 years)
2009 - 2011	Stipend for master's degree (CONACYT); 7,000 MXN per month (2 years)
2005 – 2006	Stipend for bachelor's degree (PIBIC/UFC); 300 R\$ per month (1 year)

Research experience

12/2015 - 01/2016 Volunteer, HONKO Mangrove Conservation & Education, Madagascar

project: Mangrove long-term monitoring and sustainable livelihoods (2 weeks)

activities: data management, fieldwork data collection, maintenance of research station

03/2011 - 11/2011 Technical Support Researcher (100%) (REFLORA/CNPq) at the RON Herbarium, UNIR, Brazil

<u>project</u>: Integration, qualification and provision of data related to botanical collections in the Brazilian Amazon

activities: use of Brahms software, processing and management of botanical specimens, fieldwork

Teaching experience

12/2019 **Teaching** in course *Análise de dados em R* (16h), UFC, Brazil
10/2015 - 11/2015 **Teaching assistant** in course *Plant physiology* (60h), University of Konstanz, Germany
10/2014 - 11/2014 **Teaching assistant** in course *Plant physiology* (60h), University of Konstanz, Germany

03/2011 - 10/2011 Assistant professor at distance education in course Biology, UNIR, Brazil

04/2006 - 12/2006 Teaching assistant in courses Botany and Plant anatomy and morphology, UFC, Brazil

Training

10/2021 (5 days) Epigenomics Data Analysis: from Bulk to Single Cell, National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden (NBIS)

04/2021 (4 days) Structural Equation Modelling in R, University of Cambridge

12/2020 (5 days) Introduction to Analysis of Epigenetic Data, UCDavis Bioinformatics Core

03/2017 - 09/2018 Data Analyst Nanodegree, Udacity

12/2014 | 12/2015 Introduction to Geometric Morphometrics | Geometric Morphometrics in R, Transmitting Science

Skills

Analyses common statistical methods, data modeling, data visualisation

Programming R (mostly) and proficient with python, bash, SQL, html

Software Microsoft Office, LaTeX, Inkscape, SPSS, Jupyter Notebooks, Tableau

Other cluster computing, vector image editing and version control

General interests

Nature (hiking, sightseeing), sports (cycling, climbing, swimming), reading (news and books), music (rock).

Languages

Portuguese native

EnglishfluentTOEFL: 102/120 (year 2011)GermanproficientGoethe Institute: B2.2 (year 2013)SpanishfluentEPLE/UNAM: 830/1000 (year 2008)

2/3

Publications

Carleial S, Soares M. The urgent and yet forgotten problems of current scientific and academic practice. Arq. Ciên. Mar, ISSN 2526-7639, 55, 52-62.

Carleial S, Nätt D, Unternaehrer E, Elbert T, Robjant K, Wilker S, Vukojevic V, Kolassa IT, Zeller AC, Koebach A (2021) **DNA** methylation changes following Narrative Exposure Therapy in a randomized controlled trial with female former child soldiers. Sci Rep, 11(1), 18493

Abreu L, Koebach A, Botía OMD, Carleial S, Hoeffler A, Stojez W, Freudenreich H, Justino P, Brück T (2021) Life with corona: increased gender differences in aggression and depression symptoms due to the COVID-19 pandemic burden in Germany, Front Psychol, 12: 689396

Koebach A, Carleial S, Elbert T, Schmitt S, Robjant K (2021) **Treating trauma and aggression with Narrative Exposure Therapy in former child and adult soldiers: a randomized controlled trial in Eastern DR Congo**, J Consult Clin Psychol, 89(3), 143-155

Serpeloni F, Narrog JA, de Assis SG, Avanci JQ, Carleial S, Koebach A (2021) **Narrative Exposure Therapy versus treatment as usual in a sample of trauma survivors who live under ongoing threat of violence in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: study protocol for a randomised controlled trial.** Trials, 22(1), 1-10

Unternaehrer E, Carleial S, Koebach A, Zeller A, Meinlschmidt G, Elbert T (2020) **Association between BDNF DNA methylation** and symptom improvement following cognitive-behavioral therapy in stress-related mental disorders, Psychoneuroendocrinology, 119: 105009

Robjant K, Schmitt S, Chibashimba A, Carleial S, Elbert T, Koebach A (2020) **Trauma, aggression and post conflict perpetration of community violence in female former child soldiers** – a study in Eastern DR Congo. Front Psychiatry, 11:1-10

Robjant K, Koebach A, Schmitt S, Chibashimba A, Carleial S, Elbert T (2019) The treatment of posttraumatic stress symptoms and aggression in female former child soldiers using adapted Narrative Exposure therapy – a RCT in eastern democratic republic of Congo. Behavior Res Ther, 123: 103482

Carleial S, Maurel N, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2018) **Oviposition by the Mountain Alcon Blue butterfly increases with host plant flower number and host ant abundance**. Basic Appl Ecol, 28:87-96

Carleial S, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2017) Relatively weak inbreeding depression in selfing but also outcrossing populations of North American Arabidopsis lyrata, J Evol Biol, 30: 1994-2004

Carleial S, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2017) Small reductions in corolla size and pollen:ovule ratio, but no changes in flower shape in selfing populations of the North American Arabidopsis lyrata, Oecologia, 401-413

Tedder A, Carleial S, Golebiewska M, Kappel C, Shimizu KK, Stift M (2015) **Evolution of the selfing syndrome in Arabis alpina** (**Brassicaceae**), PloS ONE, 10(6): e0126618

Carleial S, Delgado-Salinas A, Domínguez CA, Terrazas T (2015) **Reflexed flowers in Aeschynomene amorphoides (Fabaceae: Faboideae): a mechanism promoting pollination specialization?** Bot J Linn Soc, 177(4): 657-666

Carleial S, Bigio NC (2014) What survived from the PLANAFLORO Project: angiosperms of Rondônia State, Brazil, Checklist, 10(1): 33-45

in review

Carleial, S., Hoeffler, A., Koebach, A., Robjant, K., Schmitt, S. Mental health and everyday violence in the Eastern DRC

Schmitt S, Robjant K, Elbert T, Chibashimba A, Hoeffler A, Carleial S, Koebach A (2021) Breaking the cycles of violence with narrative exposure: development and feasibility of a community-based intervention for populations living under continuous threat

Stojetz et al. The life with corona survey

Peer-reviews

Am. J. Bot., AoB Plants, Aust. J. Bot., Check List, Epigenomics, PeerJ